A Finding Aid to the Katherine Thayer Hobson Papers, 1930-1982, in the Archives of American Art AAA.hobskath
Archives of American Art
Katherine Thayer Hobson papers
1930-1982
AAA.hobskath
Archives of American Art
0.6 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor Katherine Hobson Thayer measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1930 to 1982. Found within the collection are personal and professional correspondence; writings on art and anticommunist activities; printed materials; sketches; and photographs and slides of Hobson, her friends, and her artwork.
Hobson, Katherine Thayer, 1889-1982
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Katherine Thayer Hobson donated her papers to the archives in 1979. Additional material was donated by Hobson’s sister, Eleanor Hobson McKenzie, in 1982.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Sculptor Katherine Thayer Hobson (1889-1982) lived and worked in New York City. She is known for her sculptures of racehorses, war memorials, and portrait busts.
Hobson was born in Denver, Colorado and received her education in the United States and continued her art studies in Europe. Her early career focused on commissioned portrait busts, war memorials, and relief sculptures, including a relief of St. George (1945) at St. James Episcopal Church in New York City, and a World War I memorial installed in Dresden during the 1920s. In the mid-1960s, after watching the horse Buckpasser win a stakes race, Hobson sculpted his bust, after which she earned additional commissions for the racehorses Dr. Fager and Ruffian.
She was a member of the National Sculpture Society, the American Artists Professional League (AAPL), and the Society of Western Artists. Two awards, the AAPL’s Katherine Thayer Hobson Award, and Pen and Brush’s Katherine Thayer Hobson Memorial Award, are given in her honor. Hobson died in her home in New York City in 1982.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of sculptor Katherine Hobson Thayer measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1930 to 1982. Found within the collection are personal and professional correspondence; writings on art and anticommunist activities; printed materials; sketches; and photographic materials of Hobson, her friends, and her artwork.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as one series.
Series 1: Personal papers, 1930-1982 (0.6 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Anti-communist movements; Artists -- Political activity; Photographs; Sculptors--New York (State)--New York; Sketches; Women artists
- Personal Papers, 1930-1982; Series 1; 0.6 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Scope and Contents note
  Personal papers consist of professional correspondence related to gallery openings, artist representation, and potential commissions for architectural firms; personal correspondence with friends and family; and letters to government officials regarding concern over radical Communist activities. Correspondents of note responding to gallery invitations and letters of inquiry regarding commissions include: Malvina Hoffman, Leon Kroll, Colette Roberts, Eero Saarinen, Lawrence Grant White, and William Zorach. There are also two letters from the University of Gottengen and two postcards of the bust "Charlotte Muller" describing Hobson's work on those projects.
  Writings include notes and essays on art topics, as well as additional writings and miscellaneous materials related to Hobson’s anticommunist correspondence and work for the National Sculpture Society. Printed materials include art related bulletins, clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and periodicals. Sketches are figure studies and potential sculptural projects, including concept drafts for the doors of St. Peter's in Rome. Photographic materials are of Hobson and her friends, models that she employed, and documentation of her artwork. The series also includes two certificates awarded to Hobson.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged by document type. Correspondence is in chronological order.
  - Awards, 1964-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, circa 1930-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1930-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
  - Writings and Notes, circa 1930-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Writing Miscellany, circa 1930-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Anti-Communistic Activities, circa 1950-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes Wheeler Williams' report, "Confusion in the Art World," published by Awake, Inc.
  - National Sculpture Society Activities, circa 1950-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes the National Sculpture Society's 1971 Treasurer's Report.
  - Printed Materials, Bulletins, 1953-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Printed Materials, Clippings, circa 1950-1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Printed Materials, Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1953, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Printed Materials, Periodicals, 1930, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Printed Materials, Miscellaneous Materials, circa 1946-1964 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sketches, circa 1930-1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Sketches, Diocesan Garden, Cincinnati, Ohio, circa 1930-1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sketches, St. Peters Door Competition, Rome, Italy, circa 1957 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Katherine Thayer Hobson, circa 1930-1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Models, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Fountains at Berlin Park, circa 1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Head of Buckpasser, Dr. Fager,, and Ruffian, (horses), circa 1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Head of Eleanor Fitzsimmons, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Reliefs, circa 1945-1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Sculptures, circa 1930-1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Slides of Katherine Thayer Hobson and Artwork, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 8)